<products>
	<product>
		<id>0</id>
		<name>RoboDigger</name>
		<description>The RoboDigger allows your colony to expand underground, either by drilling a shaft into the planet's crust or by further excavating an existing area. The RoboDigger's drilling equipment is not far removed from the large borers used on Earth since the 19th century; however the tunneling shield was over-engineered by necessity prior to departure to withstand the hostile environment of our new home.</description>
	</product>

	<product>
		<id>1</id>
		<name>RoboDozer</name>
		<description>"The RoboDozer can grade, level, and reshape the rough terrain of this world, making it suitable for construction and road building. Capable of moving hundreds of thousands of pounds of rock and soil, the RoboDozer's low-mass, high-strength blade was originally designed to build the landing pad for a planned lunar outpost that never came to fruition.</description>
	</product>

	<product>
		<id>2</id>
		<name>RoboMiner</name>
		<description>"The RoboMiner builds mines at designated mining beacons. This action consumes the vehicle. Arguably the most advanced piece of technology brought with us from Earth, the RoboMiner deploys into a fully automated, self-sustaining mining operation, robot factory, and maintenance facility, capable of digging and drilling tunnels, extracting and retrieving ores, and repairing and replacing the hundreds of specialized robots it employs.</description>
	</product>

	<product>
		<id>3</id>
		<name>RoboExplorer</name>
		<description>"The RoboExplorer can identify additional mining locations that our initial orbital inspection missed. Equipped with an electromagnetic prospecting kit, x-ray spectrometer and mineralogy suite, and sample analysis package, this evolution of Mars rover technology is a self-sufficient geology lab on wheels.</description>
	</product>

	<product>
		<id>4</id>
		<name>Truck</name>
		<description>"Trucks are needed to carry ore from a mine to a smelter for refinement. Once assigned to a mine and smelter, trucks will automatically travel along the fastest route between these structures. Trucks travel faster over bulldozed terrain, and fastest over paved roads.</description>
	</product>

	<product>
		<id>32</id>
		<name>Clothing</name>
		<description>"Standard-issue jumpsuits are available for all colonists, but these were designed for functionality, not fashion. Offering regular clothing will allow people to demonstrate their style and individuality, improving colony morale.</description>
	</product>

	<product>
		<id>33</id>
		<name>Medicine</name>
		<description>"Medicine is a catch-all term for first-aid supplies, antibiotics, vaccines, dietary supplements, and anything else a colonist might need to stay happy and healthy. Keeping a supply of medicine will reduce our colony's mortality rate and help stop the spread of a plague in the event of an outbreak.</description>
	</product>

</products>